Hey everyone and thanks for jumping back
into the cryptoverse.
Today we're going to talk about Bitcoin
and we're going to be doing a bit of
whale watching. If you guys like the
content, make sure you subscribe to the
channel, give the video a thumbs up, and
check out the sale on Into the
Cryptoverse Premium at into the
cryptoverse.com.
You can get access to this dashboard uh
that you see on the screen. And as a
reminder, check out the upcoming ITC
conference. Ticket prices are going to
be going up on September 1st.
Let's go ahead and jump in. So on the
Into the Cryptoverse website, we have
recently launched the whale watching
dashboard and we we're actually looking
at at sort of four different areas of
what whales are doing. And and so those
four different areas are whale
transactions,
exchange activity.
So for whale transactions, it's the
equal weight average of the selected
whale transaction input scores available
on each date. And we'll talk about that
in a minute. We have exchange activity,
the equal weight average of the selected
exchange deposit, withdrawal, and flow
imbalance,
exchange inflow composition, and whale
holder positioning. Now, we have to
think about this risk metric a little
bit different than a risk metric. Whale
activity going up doesn't necessarily
mean it's bad. So, if for instance, we
were looking at whale transactions and
it were very very high right now, that
wouldn't necessarily be a bad thing.
Sometimes there's a lot of whale
activity at lows, but there's also a lot
of whale activity at highs. So arguably
a dashboard like this
doesn't it might not do the best job of
telling you like if it's a if if it's a
major low or if it's a major high but
what it could do is when there is a lot
of volatility whether it is going up or
going down in terms of the price of
Bitcoin whether it's going up or going
down if the whale activity were to pick
up significantly then it would imply
there's a decent chance that you are in
fact approaching either a local top or a
local bottom. Again, it's not going to
tell you which way it's going to go
before it gets there.
But when you are there, if you're
wondering, all right, could this be a
local top? Could this be a local bottom?
I think looking at some of the whale
activity might in fact be in insightful.
And so this all of this stuff is made up
of a lot of different things. So we have
these tables collapsed here. Um, some of
them are low just because there's not
really any any crazy transactions going
on relative to what we've seen in the
past. Um, but you have all these
different places and this is where we're
basically capturing the data that's
making up the whale activity score. So,
we're looking at like transaction count
at certain, you know, certain levels
like 1 million in in transaction value,
100,000, etc. Uh we're looking at inflow
size to exchanges and outflow size.
We're looking at um exchange inflow
share from thousand plus bitcoin
holders. We're also looking at things
like the address count holding between
100 to a,000 bitcoin and many many other
things, right? Like you can see all of
these things on this chart. Now if you I
if we look at each individual one,
right? that if you were to look at at
exchange activity for instance, let's go
in here. It's pretty noisy. And it makes
sense because, you know, Bitcoin when it
spikes or when it it goes to a low,
there's going to be a lot of noise. What
we could do is we could we could, you
know, take a moving average of it and
that would clean it up a little bit,
right? It would at least allow you to
kind of see what's going on. But this is
an example of like just because it
spikes doesn't mean it's a bad thing.
For instance, it spiked in December 2018
when the low occurred. It also spiked
going into 2020 again with the pandemic
low. So this metric, the exchange
activity score, you can also see it
spiked a lot in January, February 2015
around the market cycle bottom. So just
because it spikes isn't necessarily a
bad thing. Some of the whale activity
that we're tracking is more indicative
of sort of showing bottoms while others
might be a little bit more indicative of
showing a top. If we were to look at
whale transactions again, it's pretty
benign right now, right? Like there's
not a whole lot going on. You can see
this one tends to spike near tops as
well, right? So this one is s sort of
topping in like December 2017 in this
case like early 2021 or mid209 when we
had the apathetic top. It also spiked
over here in October of 2025 and also
near the local top in January of 2025 as
well. So this one,
the whale transaction activity score is
actually better for identifying tops.
Look at 2013 than bottoms.
But the exchange activity
seems to be a little bit maybe better at
finding lows rather than highs. So what
we've done is we've tried to sort of in
a clever way put this together into a
single whale activity score. And the
idea is that it's spiking at both tops
and bottoms. Okay. So again, is it going
to tell you ahead of time whether you're
going to go down or you're going to go
up? Like is it going to tell you if the
price of Bitcoin is going to go down or
it's going to go up? No. We have other
charts that we try to rely more for
that. But what it can do is when you're
at a top or when you're at a bottom, you
did you do tend to see this metric
spike. For instance, the end of 2017,
the you know, beginning early stages of
2021, but also spiking at the end of
2018, also spiking at the end of 2022,
spiking at the end of 2013. So the idea
is that when you have a very volatile
move in Bitcoin, whether it's to the
upside or the downside, once this metric
starts to reach pretty high activity
levels, it is often times again not a
guarantee and markets can change. No,
the past is not necessarily a predictor
of the future, but you would expect this
metric to spike and it's clearly not
spiking right now, right? like there's
just simply not a lot of whale activity
as it stands right now, but that could
certainly change in a few months. We
also of course have the exchange inflow
composition and and whale holder
positioning. Now, what's interesting is
if you if you scroll down and look at
some of the charts, you have this is the
it's showing you whale transaction count
for 100k plus, a million plus, and 10
million plus. You can see what I'm
talking about. Like if you're just
looking at transactions with a 100 thou
with 100,000 plus in in volume, there's
just not a lot going on right now,
right? Like I mean it's it's August 2026
and there's just not a lot of interest.
That doesn't mean it's going to always
be like that. There was also not a lot
of interest in 2018. In fact, we're
basically at the same level now that we
were at in August 2018. The only
difference is there wasn't this massive
spike that preceded it like in 2018.
If you look at it for a million,
guess what? It it it's really low
compared to where it's been basically
for the last several years. It's been at
these levels a couple of times, but it's
been a while. And in those cases, it did
go a little bit lower before it started
to pick back up. And then you have 10
million, which we've track also started
tracking. Um, and that that's also sort
of dropping right now as well. So if we
look at exchange flow to a lot of
different exchanges, this is a really
interesting chart because this is so
this is Bitcoin deposits from the 10
largest inflow transactions
relative to the total inflow.
Okay, so again deposits from the top the
top 10 largest inflow transactions for
that time period relative to the total
inflow.
For a long time, this metric was
actually going down
and then after 2017,
it essentially has stabilized, right?
Like it hasn't done a lot. Now, this is
actually interesting because there's
other things that have also kind of
dropped since then as well. You've seen
a lot of like all Bitcoin pairs
generally trend down since 2017. If you
look at things like the advanced decline
index of the top 100 cryptocurrencies,
that's generally been trending down. So,
if you're not familiar what I'm talking
about, there's this advanced decline
index of the top 100 cryptocurrencies
chart. Like, look at where it was in
2017 and it's basically just been down
since then. So, it's not like this what
the chart is showing is is that
surprising, but it is interesting. By
the way, for some of you, you might
remember these well-watching videos from
2022. One of the websites that I would
talk about back then was this chart uh
this website. It was a bit bid info
charts and you know you can look at a
lot of the different um addresses on
here. I mean a lot of these are just
owned by exchanges but you know you
could scroll down and and look at they
have like first in last in first out
last out. So you can kind of see the
last time uh Bitcoin was going into
these addresses or out of these
addresses. And you know I would probably
recommend not looking worrying too much
about the top several because they're
just mainly going to be exchanges. It's
not like you're going to get any great
insight. um from that. But you know, if
you scroll down like you'll find a lot
of different addresses and you'll see
that, you know, some of them been in
have been relatively active recently. Uh
and then some of them have not, right? I
mean, and I don't, you know, I don't
have any insight exactly on what each of
these ones are except for what they're
already labeled as. I mean, some of them
you can see like they are, you know,
sort of belonging to various exchanges,
but again, there are some that are not.
They're sort of we don't really know
exactly who owns it. And you can see
when they were last active or if they
just haven't been active in a long time.
Um, I mean, here's a random wallet,
right? This one, uh, it looks like
they've been active relatively recently,
right? As recently as today, right? Uh,
so again, like, you know, it's kind of
an interesting thing. There's also tons
of addresses that just have like, you
know, 10,000 Bitcoin in them, right? You
can see 10,000 each. Um, and then
there's addresses that haven't
transaction transacted in a while,
right? Like if you look at whoever
wallet 90 is, they have 9,800 Bitcoin in
here. Um, and you know, I mean, I guess
I guess they did have one in April of
this year. So, that's not too long ago.
that was uh as last in. But I mean,
there's some there's some on here that
that you know, if you keep if you scroll
for a little bit, you'll find that it's
been a while since they've, you know,
since they've done any any uh
transactions. Maybe they just kind of
fell off for a little bit. They don't
they're not looking at it as much
anymore. Um but yeah, I mean, it's kind
of an interesting website to go through
now. And I don't remember if there's any
um like I mean, look at look at this
random one right here, right? over the
last 30 days, you can see that it it's
been adding. So, if you click on it, um
I guess we do have to do security
verification, right? But if you click on
it, um you can, you know, you can see
the balance
like they they added a little bit in uh
July. You can see that, right? A modest
5,900 Bitcoin in July of 2026.
So anyways,
going back to the well watching
dashboard, you can scroll down. This one
here basically just shows you uh you
know various bitcoin supplies by address
balance. And so you could you know you
could isolate whichever one you want and
and in this case the bitcoin supply held
by addresses with 1 and 10,000 bitcoin
that's actually been dropping um you
know for basically since 2021 that's
been dropping between 100 and a,000.
that's actually been trending up
between 10,000 and 100,000 been trending
down between 100,000 and a million. It's
basically remained relatively flat. So,
it's it's interesting in the sense that
you can see that there's more addresses
that are having between say 100 and
a,000 Bitcoin
and fewer for like a,000 to 10,000. So
like if you look at between a,000 and
10,000 that's gone from like 30%.
Down to like almost 20 but 100 to a,000
has gone up from 20 you know up to like
25 26. So there's just like re there's
this redistribution
of of Bitcoin essentially.
And then here's a really similar chart.
Uh it just shows Bitcoin address um a
bitcoin address count by balance. So
this is the supply by address balance.
This is the address count by balance.
And you can see that it's been you know
generally trending down for a lot of
those larger ones. We also have live
whale positioning which you can see um
you can look at at some of the different
positions that you have on here and and
the position size bucket. We've got
different distributions like you know
the small whale, the large whale, uh the
tidal whale, the Leviathan, um which
ones are winning, which ones are losing,
which wallets are bullish, which ones
lean bearish, um and and the list goes
on and on. So, we got a lot on the
website now uh as far as well watching
goes. If you're interested, make sure
you guys check it out. Links in the
description below. Hopefully, this will
be another dashboard that can be used to
try to help identify not if the next
move is going to be to the upside or the
downside, but when the move occurs, it
can maybe help figure out around the
time that it actually might come to an
end. And that's normally whenever you
see big spikes, large spikes in whale
activity. So, hopefully you enjoyed this
edition of whale watching. It's been
about four years since we did one of
these videos, but I thought it would be
interesting to do, especially since
we're getting into crunch time, getting
closer to the end of the mid midterm
year. Let's see what happens with the
whale wallet activity and if we start to
see it really change over the coming
months. If you guys like the content,
make sure you subscribe. Give the video
a thumbs up to get access. Go to into
the cryptoverse.com. Make sure you also
get your ticket to the ITC conference
before September 1st. Ticket prices are
going up on September 1st and the
conference is not until uh November 20th
through the 22nd. Thank you guys for
tuning in. Subscribe and I'll see you
next time.